<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-07-04T15:48:41+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Evolutionary Systems Genetics</title><subtitle>Evolutionary systems genetics - J-P Verta - Post-doc at the University of Helsinki interested in evolution, genetics and conservation.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Popularized Science Article Out</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/06/21/Popularized-science-article-out.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Popularized Science Article Out" /><published>2018-06-21T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-06-21T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/06/21/Popularized-science-article-out</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/06/21/Popularized-science-article-out.html">&lt;p&gt;A popularized science article I wrote about our groups findings of the salmon maturation gene vgll3 and how this can be used to guide angling practices came out today. Conveniently on my b-day! Ex-Primmer lab member Mikko Ellmen provided spectacular photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/figures/ClassyFlyFishingMagazineArticle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A popularized science article I wrote about our groups findings of the salmon maturation gene vgll3 and how this can be used to guide angling practices came out today. Conveniently on my b-day! Ex-Primmer lab member Mikko Ellmen provided spectacular photos.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I Love Fieldwork</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/05/18/Why-I-love-fieldwork.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I Love Fieldwork" /><published>2018-05-18T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-05-18T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/05/18/Why-I-love-fieldwork</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/05/18/Why-I-love-fieldwork.html">&lt;p&gt;The reason is moments like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/figures/fieldWorkGoldenMoment.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The reason is moments like this.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Public Outreach On Salmon Research And Conservation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/05/02/Public-outreach-on-salmon-research-and-conservation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Public Outreach On Salmon Research And Conservation" /><published>2018-05-02T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-05-02T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/05/02/Public-outreach-on-salmon-research-and-conservation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/05/02/Public-outreach-on-salmon-research-and-conservation.html">&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to Helsinki Spey Clave for the opportunity to talk about the
importance of big salmon conservation! The Helsinki-based fly-fishing
shop was very kind to slot me some time during their “Season Starter”
event to talk about recent findings on the genetics of Atlantic salmon
age at maturity and what this means for anglers. Awesome event with many
intelligent questions and attentive anglers in the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/figures/HSCpublicOutreach.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Many thanks to Helsinki Spey Clave for the opportunity to talk about the importance of big salmon conservation! The Helsinki-based fly-fishing shop was very kind to slot me some time during their “Season Starter” event to talk about recent findings on the genetics of Atlantic salmon age at maturity and what this means for anglers. Awesome event with many intelligent questions and attentive anglers in the audience.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Site migration to GitHub</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/04/30/site-migration.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Site migration to GitHub" /><published>2018-04-30T10:17:47+03:00</published><updated>2018-04-30T10:17:47+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/04/30/site-migration</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/04/30/site-migration.html">&lt;p&gt;Hello world! I switched to GitHub and Jekyll for maintaining this site. Please bear with me while I set this site up.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Hello world! I switched to GitHub and Jekyll for maintaining this site. Please bear with me while I set this site up.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meeting For Early Career Scientists In Salmonid Research Nowpas 2018</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/03/21/Meeting-for-early-career-scientists-in-salmonid-research-NoWPaS-2018.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meeting For Early Career Scientists In Salmonid Research Nowpas 2018" /><published>2018-03-21T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-03-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/03/21/Meeting-for-early-career-scientists-in-salmonid-research-NoWPaS-2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/03/21/Meeting-for-early-career-scientists-in-salmonid-research-NoWPaS-2018.html">&lt;p&gt;In March 2018 I had the pleasure to attend to a conference for early-career scientists working on anadromous salmonids. With only the four keynote speakers being senior scientists (Andrew Hendry from McGill Uni, Pauliina Louhi from Parks &amp;amp; Wildlife Finland, Katja Anttila from Uni Turku and Craig Primmer from Uni Helsinki), we truly were a young and jolly crew of 32 fish lovers. I felt amongst fellow freaks from the moment we arrived at the Oulanka research station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/figures/nowpas2018.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being around such energetic and enthusiastic scientists really gave a big motivation push for getting back to the lab as soon as possible and roll up my sleeves. I was impressed by the quality of the presentations, ranging from genomics to behavior and management. I feel confident to say this was the most high-quality workshop I’ve ever taken part, relative to the experience of the participants. It also made it clear that the expectation in the field is to be nothing less than excellent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have felt the need to partake in practical efforts to help our endangered salmon and trout populations back here in Finland. Meeting the key young scientists working on salmon conservation was a first and crucial step seeing that I’ve been away for so long and new to salmonid research. I’m hoping that I can be of help to them and the larger conservation community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t mentioned anything about off-topic activities, but I’m sure you can imagine that the atmosphere among a bunch of young scientists stuck in the middle of nowhere cannot be anything but hilarious. The absolute activity-hit was the Finnish spa a.k.a. hole in the ice :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/figures/icehole.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next year, NoWPaS!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In March 2018 I had the pleasure to attend to a conference for early-career scientists working on anadromous salmonids. With only the four keynote speakers being senior scientists (Andrew Hendry from McGill Uni, Pauliina Louhi from Parks &amp;amp; Wildlife Finland, Katja Anttila from Uni Turku and Craig Primmer from Uni Helsinki), we truly were a young and jolly crew of 32 fish lovers. I felt amongst fellow freaks from the moment we arrived at the Oulanka research station.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Moving To New Adventures At The University Of Helsinki</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/12/14/Moving-to-new-adventures-at-the-University-of-Helsinki.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moving To New Adventures At The University Of Helsinki" /><published>2017-12-14T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-12-14T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/12/14/Moving-to-new-adventures-at-the-University-of-Helsinki</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/12/14/Moving-to-new-adventures-at-the-University-of-Helsinki.html">&lt;p&gt;After three years in Tübingen time has come for heading towards new adventures. I have the great pleasure and honour to join Craig Primmer and his wonderful team of very motivated scientists at the University of Helsinki in Finland. To me it will be a change in systems, moving from stickleback to salmon, but the overall theme remains the same - molecular gene regulation and it’s link to adaptive traits. Bets are increasing and I will work on my most challenging scientific question thus far when I will try to dissect the molecular mechanisms of sex-dependent dominance in age-at-maturity in salmon. On another level, it will be a return to home after almost ten years of academic life abroad. And hopefully much more fishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/figures/JPandSalmon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">After three years in Tübingen time has come for heading towards new adventures. I have the great pleasure and honour to join Craig Primmer and his wonderful team of very motivated scientists at the University of Helsinki in Finland. To me it will be a change in systems, moving from stickleback to salmon, but the overall theme remains the same - molecular gene regulation and it’s link to adaptive traits. Bets are increasing and I will work on my most challenging scientific question thus far when I will try to dissect the molecular mechanisms of sex-dependent dominance in age-at-maturity in salmon. On another level, it will be a return to home after almost ten years of academic life abroad. And hopefully much more fishing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">R Markdown For Teaching</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/11/23/R-Markdown-for-teaching.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="R Markdown For Teaching" /><published>2017-11-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-11-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/11/23/R-Markdown-for-teaching</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/11/23/R-Markdown-for-teaching.html">&lt;p&gt;A colleague of mine recently introduced me to a useful tool for creating, managing and sharing R code. We are both part of a team teaching a practical course on the statistical programming language R, and my colleague proposed that we would organise the workshops as R Markdown Notebooks. What an excellent idea!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are used to working with R Studio on your local computer implementing your code as R Markdown is really simple. I usually work on our campus server, and organise my code as scripts for simplicity. I found that R Markdown is nevertheless an excellent tool for teaching, and makes workshops in general easier for all parties. Here’s how it &lt;a href=&quot;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/lesson-1.html&quot;&gt;works&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic idea is that instead of a script that you execute, you organise your work as a interactive “notebook” (a bit like &lt;a href=&quot;https://jupyter-notebook-beginner-guide.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;jupyter&lt;/a&gt; for Python code). For teaching, I found this very helpful as I can organise my tutorials around code examples that the student execute on their computers while still properly explaining the ideas. I found it helpful to have the more theory-heavy text and the hands-on exercise integrated into one smooth workflow. In addition, organising your tutorial as a Markdown file allows the students to keep all that information in a easily accessible format or even print it out as a neat pdf. Give it a try!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A colleague of mine recently introduced me to a useful tool for creating, managing and sharing R code. We are both part of a team teaching a practical course on the statistical programming language R, and my colleague proposed that we would organise the workshops as R Markdown Notebooks. What an excellent idea!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Recap Of Cnrs Jacques Monod Conference</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/10/19/Recap-of-CNRS-Jacques-Monod-conference.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recap Of Cnrs Jacques Monod Conference" /><published>2017-10-19T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-10-19T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2017/10/19/Recap-of-CNRS-Jacques-Monod-conference</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/10/19/Recap-of-CNRS-Jacques-Monod-conference.html">&lt;p&gt;Roscoff, France is a charming old port with excellent weather, food and science. From 10th to 14th October, CNRS biological station hosted the Jacques Monod conference in evolutionary genomics and systems biology. The intimate conference was a huge success, bringing together leading scientists in evolutionary genomics, population genetics and systems biology. The hundred-odd participants were spoiled with latest advances in understanding the evolutionary processes that govern the evolution of sex, adaptation and biological complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking back on the week, a few thoughts have sticked particularly well in mind. Many groups demonstrated that from bacteria to yeast and fruit flies, adaptation does’t seem to be “mutation limited”. Many of these observations indicate that of the three textbook forces that govern evolution - mutation, natural selection and drift - the two latter are the most important when thinking of how populations evolve and adapt over time. In other words, many cases suggest that populations do not need to “wait for adaptive mutations” in order to adapt. Instead, the raw material for evolutionary change seems to exist as standing variation, or emerges fast, so that adaptive processes are principally governed by the balance between selection and drift. These are remarkable findings and sure to raise discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another remarkable trend that emerged clear and concise from the presentations last week were studies of the evolution of biological complexity that bridge systems biology with evolutionary processes. The mix of talks from systems biology and evolution was clever from the part of the organisers, and at least for me helped to really understand that some excellent systems biology science has clear (and testable) evolutionary consequences. As an example, studies of compensatory evolution by Csaba Pal from Hungary imply clear evolutionary hypotheses: epistasis in fitness gains should be widespread and speciation could be completely due to compensatory evolution that remediates the fitness effects of deleterious mutations (without a hint of directional selection!). Cool hypotheses which are worth testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all I had a great week in Roscoff, with plenty of cutting edge science, lots of new contacts and excellent scientific discussions. Without forgetting delicious French cuisine, of course.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Roscoff, France is a charming old port with excellent weather, food and science. From 10th to 14th October, CNRS biological station hosted the Jacques Monod conference in evolutionary genomics and systems biology. The intimate conference was a huge success, bringing together leading scientists in evolutionary genomics, population genetics and systems biology. The hundred-odd participants were spoiled with latest advances in understanding the evolutionary processes that govern the evolution of sex, adaptation and biological complexity.</summary></entry></feed>